Finding Aid for University of Michigan Alumnae Club of Ann Arbor, Margaret L. Waterman Group records
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
University of Michigan Alumnae Club of Ann Arbor, Margaret L. Waterman Group records 1955-2010
University of Michigan. Alumnae Club of Ann Arbor. Margaret L. Waterman Group.
3 oversize volumes
2.25 linear feet
8712 Bimu H6 2
Ann Arbor, Michigan, group of University of Michigan Alumnae Club. Notebooks containing minutes, correspondence, reports and printed miscellanea.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The records were received form donor # 7092.
Periodic additions to the records expected.
The records are open without restriction.
The Margaret Lawlor Waterman Group forms part of the Ann Arbor Alumnae Association and works alongside the University of Michigan Alumni Association to promote the advancement of University of Michigan students and alumni. The Waterman Group formed in 1953 as an off-shoot of the Lucille B. Conger Group of the University of Michigan Alumnae in Ann Arbor.
On May 28, 1953, the new members of the Waterman Group, then called the New Michigan Alumnae Club, held a membership tea and dessert, followed by an election and business meeting. Later in 1953, the group changed its name to the Margaret Lawlor Waterman Group, in honor of Margaret Lawlor Waterman (1924-1926), wife of business professor Merwin H. Waterman, member of the Michigan Alumnae Club of Ann Arbor, former director and vice-president of the University Alumnae Association board of development, member of the board of the Michigan League and the Alumnae Council, and past president of the Sara Browne Smith Group of the Michigan Alumnae.
The Waterman Group was originally conceived of as an "evening group" for young university graduates who might prefer evening meetings rather than the Alumnae Club's daytime gatherings. Membership in the group was open to women graduates of the University, women that attended the university, wives of alumni or faculty, and women who had "a vital interest" in the university. The Waterman Group worked alongside Ann Arbor's other female alumnae groups, like the Lucille B. Conger Group and the Sara Browne Smith Group, to promote interest in the university, to encourage relationships between current students and alumnae, and to raise scholarship money for female students at the university.
Beginning in the 1950s the Waterman Group raised money for its scholarship fund through sponsorship of an annual puppet show for local children. In 1972, the group inaugurated its Town Hall Lecture Series with guest Kitty Carlisle, to raise funds for the its scholarships. The Town Hall series invites four lecturers a year to the Ann Arbor area, where they speak on a range of topics, from politics and current events, to humor, science, the arts, fashion, and culture. Past guests have included Rosamond Bernier, Donald Brooks, Dr. Joyce Brothers, Ken Burns, Hume Cronyn and Jessica Tandy, Dr. Sanjay Gupta, Jean-Pierre Hallet, Olivia de Havilland, G. Gordon Liddy, Art Linkletter, George Plimpton, Claire Shipman, Martha Stewart, Helen Thomas, and Pauline Trigère.
Margaret Lawlor Waterman Group Presidents
1953-1954 Louise Findlayson
1954-1955 Edith Fonde
1954-1956 Peggy Laird
1956-1957 Pat Harbaugh
1957-1958 Jeanette Schneeberger
1958-1959 Gretchen Hadler
1959-1960 Pricilla Klavitter
1960-1961 Kris Clark
1961-1962 Mary Alice Shulman
1962-1963 Jean Dickinson
1963-1964 Jean Cumminsky
1964-1965 Sarah Lampert
1965-1966 Linda McKenney
1966-1967 Betty Jo Kolb
1967-1968 Sallie Springer
1968-1969 Patti Lawson
1969-1970 Barbara Mueller
1970-1971 Cynthia Postmus
1971-1972 Virginia Castor
1972-1973 Marilynn Magoon
1973-1974 Connie Cress
1974-1975 Charlotte Portz
1975-1976 Miney Williams
1976-1977 Sally Jo Kleinschmidt
1977-1978 Ann Benner
1978-1979 Betty Pierce
1979-1980 Jane Peterson
1980-1981 Ruth Kerschbaum
1981-1982 Beverly Bole
1982-1983 Marilyn Sichler
1983-1984 Nancy Cassidy
1984-1985 Betty Graham
1985-1986 Ginny Hills
1986-1987 Terri Bartholomew
1987-1988 Rita Bencuya
1988-1989 Connie Olson
1989-1990 Pat Rigot
1990-1991 Sally Rogers
1991-1992 Barbara Stephenson
1992-1993 Joanne Cage
1993-1994 Charlotte Hanson
1994-1995 Peg Molin
1995-1996 Emily Salvette
1996-1997 Mary Kinley
1997-1998 Mary Kinley
1998-1999 Patty Tupper
1999-2000 Sally Kennedy
2000-2001 Beverley Burlingame
2001-2002 Kathryn Trim
2002-2003 Beth Williams
2003-2004 Tanya Keller
2004-2005 Marcy Teppo
2005-2006 Dona Lawson
2006-2007 Victoria Buckler
2007-2008 Joanne Hertler
2008-2009 Carolyn Shear
The Alumnae Club Margaret L. Waterman Group records are organized into three series: Records, Alumnae Council Collected Materials, and Scrapbooks. The collection includes notebooks of past presidents, meeting minutes, correspondence, planning materials, reports, lecture programs, printed miscellanea, and scrapbooks.
SCOPE CONTENT
Subjects:
Ann Arbor (Mich.); University of Michigan. Alumnae Club.; University of Michigan--Alumni and alumnae--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Waterman, Margaret L.; Women--Michigan--Ann Arbor--Societies and clubs.; University of Michigan. Alumnae Club of Ann Arbor. Margaret L. Waterman Group.
- Records 1954-2009
  The Records series, 1945-2009, (1.5 linear feet) includes club constitutions, nonprofit incorporation records, presidents' reports, financial records, correspondence, membership rosters, Town Hall Lecture Series materials and programs, and puppet show records and program materials.
  - Constitution (Box 1)
  - Corporation Paperwork (Box 1)
  - Financial Reports (Box 1)
  - Minutes (General, Board, and Annual Meetings)
    - 1955-1967 (Box 1)
    - 1967-1981 (Box 1)
  - Presidents' Notes and Records
    - 1954 (Box 1)
    - 1965-1966 (Box 1)
    - 1966-1967 (Box 1)
    - 1967-1968 (Box 1)
    - 1968-1969 (Box 1)
    - 1969-1970 (Box 1)
    - 1970-1971 (Box 1)
    - 1971-1972 (Box 1)
    - 1972-1973, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - 1973-1974, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - 1974-1975, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - 1975-1976, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - 1976-1977, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - 1977-1978, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - 1978-1979, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - 1979-1980, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - 1980-1981 (Box 2)
    - 1981-1982 (Box 2)
    - 1982-1983 (Box 2)
    - 1983-1984 (Box 2)
    - 1984-1985 (Box 2)
    - 1985-1986 (Box 2)
    - 1986-1987 (Box 2)
    - 1987-1988 (Box 2)
    - 1988-1989, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - 1989-1990 (Box 2)
    - 1990-1991 (Box 2)
    - 1991-1992 (Box 2)
    - 1992-1993 (Box 2)
    - 1993-1994 (Box 2)
    - 1994-1995 (Box 2)
    - 1995-1996 (Box 2)
    - 1996-1997 (Box 2)
    - 1997-1998 (Box 2)
    - 1998-1999 (Box 2)
    - 1999-2000 (Box 2)
    - 2000-2001 (Box 2)
    - 2001-2002 (Box 2)
    - 2002-2003 (Box 2)
    - 2003-2004 (Box 2)
    - 2004-2005 (Box 2)
    - 2005-2006 (Box 2)
    - 2006-2007 (Box 2)
    - 2007-2008 (Box 2)
    - 2008-2009 (Box 2)
    - 2009-2010 (Box 2)
  - Special Projects
    - Puppet Shows
      - 1964-1967 (Box 2)
      - 1970-1973 (Box 2)
    - Paper Sales,1954-1972 (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
- Alumnae Council Collected Materials 1971-1980
  Records in the Alumnae Council Collected Materials series, 1971-1980, (.25 linear feet) include Ann Arbor Alumnae Council minutes, board reports, agendas, and program materials.
  - Miscellaneous
    - Undated (Box 2)
    - 1971-1972 (Box 2)
    - 1972-1973 (Box 2)
    - 1973-1974 (Box 2)
    - 1974-1975 (Box 3)
    - 1976-1977 (Box 3)
    - 1977-1978 (Box 3)
    - 1978-1979 (Box 3)
    - 1979-1980 (Box 3)
- Scrapbooks 1953-2004
  The Scrapbooks series, 1953-2004, (3 oversize volumes) includes newspaper clippings, photographs, Town Hall programs, and ephemera documenting fifty-one years of the group's history, members, and events.
  - 1953-1978 (Volume 1)
  - 1975-2000 (Volume 2)
  - 2000-2004 (Volume 3)